בוקר טוב Boker Tov today’s דף Daf is מ"ח Mem Ches on
סנהדרין Sanhedrin 48. We pick up at the bottom of מ"ז עמוד
ב', Mem Zayin Amud Beis, which is איתמר. Itmar. It is the
line starts with איסלי Islei and it is ten lines from the
bottom. And you know we’re right now in the middle because it
discussed the מיתת בית דין Misas Beis Din and how they would
execute a person. We’ll get a lot more of that in the
next פרק Perek and the prohibition about letting the body, if somebody
that is being hanged, to remain overnight, leads to a much broader
conversations about general about the burial of the dead, you know, the
prohibition of הלנת המת, Halanas HaMeis, leaving the body overnight unless it’s
לכבודו L'khvodo for the honor of the person being buried. And then
that got into a whole דף Daf conversation about what is the
basis for the idea that there’s an actual obligation to bury in
the ground. And then that got into a conversation about whether the
purpose of קבורה, Kevurah, of burial, is primarily for atonement for the
dead or is it for that the body should not be ביזיון,
Bizayon, should not be a disgrace to be leaving it unburied. And
the גמרא Gemara made some interesting נפקא מינות. Nafka Minos. Then the
question about the purpose of the הספד, Hesped, the eulogy—is it for
the living, is it for the dead?
And then the גמרא Gemara got into the question about whether somebody
who is executed, if they by the court, if that actually serves
as a כפרה. Kaparah. And that then led to another conversation—this is
yesterday—about when exactly the אבילות Aveisus begins. The אבילות Aveisus begins סתימת
הגולל, Stimas HaGolel, you know רש"י Rashi would sort of say the
cover of the coffin is what that refers to, תוספות Tosfos says
it refers to a headstone when there is a headstone, but anyway
is that when does the אבילות Aveisus precisely begin and when does
the כפרה Kaparah precisely begin? So a lot of very important issues
here in general relating to the מצוה Mitzvah of burial and related
הלכות Halachos and אבילות. Aveisus. And then the גמרא Gemara got into
the issue about
the איסורי הנאה, Issurei Hana'ah, that a corpse is forbidden to derive
benefit. And there was a whole question about people that used the
dirt from where, you know, from where רב Rav was buried, and
that שמואל Shmuel
said it's okay, I mean, whatever, superstitious, a lot of other things,
but it’s not אסור בהנאה, Asur Be'hana'ah, it’s only קרקע עולם, Karka
Olam, it’s only the ground, you know, as opposed to something that
was built on top of the grave for the dead, which would
be something that was תלוש ולבסוף חיברו, Talush U'levsof Chibro, originally undetached
and now attached, and that actually when it’s being done for the
corpse is connected to the corpse, is seen as conceptually connected and
forbidden in הנאה. Hana'ah. And that gets us to the discussion today,
which starts with like at what stage will something be considered connected
to the corpse and be forbidden in הנאה, Hana'ah, but it also
has broader implications and the question is הזמנה מילתא, Hazmanah Milsa, is
designating something—like זימון Zimmun is when you like call people to בענטשן,
Bentch, like להזמין Lehazmin is to invite—is designating something without actually yet
using it for that purpose, does it give it a status or
not? So let's take a look. איתמר, Itmar, it was taught: האורג
בגד למת, HaOreg Beged LeMeis, if somebody is weaving a garment for
a shrouds for a corpse, it’s going to be important the person
is already dead, it’s a corpse. So because now this is being
made for the sake of the dead person, is it considered like
an extension connected and therefore similarly forbidden in benefit or does it
will it have to wait until it actually is used for that
purpose? So האורג בגד למת, HaOreg Beged LeMeis,
אביי Abaye אמר Amar אסור, Asur, it's forbidden, ורבא VRava אמר Amar
מותר, Mutar, it's permissible. אביי Abaye אמר Amar אסור Asur הזמנה מילתא,
Hazmanah Milsa, designating counts, and that gives it its status. Now one
should note that it’s not just verbal designating, it’s designating through an
action, but nevertheless preparing something is meaningful even if it’s not yet
used and it gives it the status.
ורבא VRava אמר Amar מותר, Mutar, it’s permissible, הזמנה לאו מילתא, Hazmanah
Lav Milsa, no, it’s not meaningful until you actually began using it.
And that is a tier specifically about shroud, but it's a general
debate of הזמנה מילתא Hazmanah Milsa or not, when something gets its
halachic status. הי מאי? Hai Mai? Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this: הזמנה
מילתא. Hazmanah Milsa. מאי טעמא דאביי? Mai Ta'ama D'Abaye? What’s the reasoning
of אביי? Abaye? גמר שם שם מעגלה ערופה. Gamar Sham Sham Me'Eglah
Arufah. Where are other things that we know are forbidden in הנאה?
Hana'ah? Well, an עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, when you take the calf
into the wadi and you break its neck for, you know, a
murder victim that you don’t know who slayed. And that says, you
know, that you shall leave it שם בנחל, Sham B'Nachal, you leave
it in the wadi and from there they learn, you know, that
the idea that the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah is forbidden in הנאה.
Hana'ah. And it says also by the dead, it says, you know,
the word שם, Sham,
by מרים, Miriam, it says ותמת שם מרים, Vatamas Sham Miriam, so
מה עגלה ערופה דהזמנה מיתסרה, Ma Eglah Arufah DeHazmanah Mitasra, the same
way the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah becomes forbidden even before you break
its neck. neck just because when you bring it down into the
wadi,
therefore, so if you take a look at רש"י Rashi the last
line the first of the widest lines, עגלת ערופה בזמן מצוה דקיימא
לן ירידתה לנחל איתן היא אוסרתה, Eglat Arufah bazman mitzvah de'kaimalan yeridata
lenachal eytan hi osarta, just bringing it into the wadi makes it
forbidden even though it has not yet actually been had its neck
broken. So האי נמי בזמן מצוה, hai nami bazman mitzvah, the same
is true therefore by things relating to the dead. When you designate
something for the dead, that is enough. Now we don't know is
that a general principle by all things or it's specifically גזירה שוה
gezerah shavah by the dead, we don't know what the application would
be by things by, you know, everything else in the halachic universe.
All right, we'll see. ורבא ve'Rava גמר, gamar, now רבא Rava says
שם שם מעבודה כוכבים sham sham me'avodah kochavim also specifically the שם
sham by death, ותמת שם מרים, Vatamos Sham Miriam, but the שם
sham when it speaks to עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, אשר עבדו שם
הגוים. Asher avdu sham hagoyim. So מה עבודה כוכבים בזמן לא מצוה,
ma avodah kochavim bazman lo mitzvah, the same way עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah is not forbidden by just designating something, you know, for עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, as the גמרא Gemara calls it אין הקדש לעבודה
זרה. ein hekdesh l'avodah zarah. So if somebody says, you know, says
I'm going to donate this house to עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, I'm
going to donate this ox to עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, there is
a that doesn't give it its status until it actually is put
to use together with the idol. So, so אף הכא נמי בזמן
לא מצוה, af hacha nami bazman lo mitzvah, here too just designating
it does not give it its status until it actually is used
with the dead body. Again a similar question, is רבא Rava saying
this specifically by מת mes or does that become a general principle?
But anyway רבא Rava uses עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah as his model
and אביי Abaye uses עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah and the גמרא Gemara
very nicely now asks what is the difference between the two models,
why does one go with one one go the other? ורבא מאי
טעמא לא גמר מעגלה ערופה? ve'Rava mai ta'ama lo gamar me'Eglah Arufah?
Why did רבא Rava not say עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah where you
see הזמנה hazmanah is meaningful? So אמר
לך amar lecha top of מ"ח עמוד א', mem chet amud aleph,
משמש ממשמש גמרינן לאפוקי עגלה ערופה דהיא גופא קדושה. meshamesh mi'meshamesh gamrinan
lafukei Eglah Arufah de'hi gufah kedushah. Okay, קדושה kedushah being used loosely
here. So we are learning an idea of something that is a
משמש meshamesh like an appurtenance, something that is connected to the main
thing. There's something main that is forbidden בהנאה b'hana'ah and what gives
this appurtenance the status of being connected to the main thing? So
that is very analogous between עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and the מת.
mes. עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, when do
things that are תשמישי עבודה זרה, tashmishei avodah zarah, נוי עבודה זרה
noy avodah zarah used with it, decorative of it, only when they're
actually put into use and placed on it or put into use?
Similarly when does something connect the dead body, the corpse is אסור
בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, when does something become connected to it? Also not
when it's designated but only when it's put in use. Very, very
nice analogy. You start with the forbidden thing, when does something else
become connected to it? Only when it's put in use. And that's
not similar to the עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah. The עגלה ערופה Eglah
Arufah you're making the thing itself forbidden and that maybe, you know,
could come at an early stage like an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
becomes forbidden if somebody designates something as the actual idol. Okay, that's
a different story. But to get a status of an appurtenance, that's
only when it's put into use. ואביי מאי טעמא לא גמר מעבודה
כוכבים? v'Abaye mai ta'ama lo gamar me'avodah kochavim? And why does אביי
Abaye not learn from עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? אמר לך מידי דאורחא
ממידי דאורחא. amar lecha midi d'orcha mi'midi d'orcha.
I want to compare עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah and a garment for
a dead body, which are things that are like somebody is it
says natural, normal, but you normally don't take a calf and break
its neck and hopefully you normally don't find murder victims, but it
means those are operating within the halachic universe, right? Those are doing
things you're supposed to be doing. And therefore when you're doing something
when you're supposed to be doing, making a shroud for a corpse,
bringing the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah in, as soon as you designate
it it gets its status לאפוקי עבודה כוכבים דלאו אורחא. lafukei avodah
kochavim d'lav orcha. עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, people should not be worshipping
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, even non-Jews should not, so we're not going
to give it its status until it's actually put into use. So
that you understand אביי's Abaye point as well, if something is sort
of how you're supposed to halachically be doing something then it gets
its status, you know, earlier. Now you're not necessarily obligated to do
it like the גמרא Gemara will talk about, you know, other things
that are connected to the dead that are not the shrouds, that
are not sort of seen as obligatory, but nevertheless, you know, in
the if that is sort of the norm and certainly if it's
obligated in some of these cases, הזמנה hazmanah suffices. So that's the
debate. Let's take a look, okay, and now we're going to see
that the we're going to assume and the very phrase הזמנה מילתא
לאו מילתא hazmanah milsa lav milsa is a very generic phrase, it's
not הזמנה למת. hazmanah l'mes. So even though it made a גזירה
שוה שם שם gezerah shavah sham sham in the end of the
day we're going to assume that what we find by the dead
becomes the general rule for all things, whether for אביי הזמנה מילתא
Abaye hazmanah milsa and רבא הזמנה לאו מילתא. Rava hazmanah lav milsa.
מיתיבי, meitvei, I'll ask you, כיפה שתמי מדרס. kippa she'tamei midras. So
you have a, you know, a handkerchief like for the head, a
head covering that is טמי tamei because of of a trodding, meaning
that it's a type of a head covering but you can also
lie down and use it as a pillow and put rest your
head on it. I guess wrap it up and use it as
a pillow. And therefore it is something that you either sit on
or lie on or stand on and that has the טומאה *tumah*
of מדרס *midras*. If a זב *zav* or זבה *zava* sits on
it, it becomes an אב הטומאה *av hatumah*. It doesn't go one
degree down, but a משכב *mishkav* or מושב *moshav* of a זב
*zav* becomes an אב הטומאה *av hatumah* and that is only specifically
things that are used for sitting on or lying on. So this
thing because it was a head scarf and could be used for
a pillow and then a זב *zav* actually did lie down on
it, it is considered, it now has the טומאה *tumah* of מדרס
*midras*. It's an אב הטומאה *av hatumah*. Now, כיפה של חוטא טמאה
מדרס *kippa shel huta tmeia midras*. ונתנו לספר *unasnu l'sefer* and you
decided, no, I'm actually going to use this to wrap my ספר
תורה Sefer Torah *Sefer Torah* or to wrap any book, use it
as a type of a gartel or a scarf or a covering,
and you've reapplied it to a type of a thing that cannot
be a מדרס *midras*, cannot be a משכב *mishkav* or מושב *moshav*
because it is not made when it's used to cover a ספר
sefer *sefer*, it would never be used for sitting or lying on.
So טהור מן המדרס *tahor min hamidras*, that changes its status. It
no longer is טמא מדרס *tamei midras*, it's no longer considered a
משכב *mishkav* or מושב *moshav*, because it's no longer, that's no longer
a use of it. אבל טמא מגע מדרס *aval tamei maga midras*.
We'll go with our גרסא *girsa* which is רש"י's Rashi *Rashi's* גרסא
*girsa*, but it is טמא *tamei* having touched a מדרס *midras*. It's
a ראשון *rishon*. It doesn't become טהור *tahor* completely. How does it
become a ראשון *rishon*? It's very, it's a fascinating idea because it's
touching itself. So in that moment of transition, it stops being a
מדרס *midras* and it's just being a normal כלי *kli*, but it's
also touching itself and as a normal כלי *kli* it touched a
מדרס *midras* itself, a משכב *mishkav* or מושב *moshav*, so it becomes
a ראשון *rishon*. Anyway, the point being that it's enough to redesignate
it and without even using it. So that shows that הזמנה מילתא
hazmanah milsa, *hazmana milsa* and it gives it its status when it's
redesignated for something else. Now there's actually a problem here because there's
two problems which is number one, even אביי Abaye *Abaye* was only
talking about when you wove a garment for the dead. He didn't
say you just verbally designated it. הזמנה hazmana, *hazmana* might have to
be הזמנה hazmana. *hazmana* through an action. The other problem is that
the general principle is כל הכלים יורדים לידי טומאתן במחשבה ואין עולים
מידי טומאתן אלא בשינוי מעשה *kol hakelim yordim lidei tumasan b'machshava v'ein
olim midei tumasan ela b'shinui ma'aseh*, that for something to, that became
טמא *tamei*, to change its status, you need to actually make a
change in the thing itself. Designation is not enough. So those two
questions might answer one another. תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says that we might
be talking here when it says נתנו לספר *nasnu l'sefer*, you designated
it, means you made some change in it in order to make
it usable for a ספר *sefer*. But you haven't used it yet.
So therefore you see just designating maybe with an action is enough
to change the status even though you haven't used it yet. That's
a proof to אביי Abaye *Abaye* and clearly we're talking about a
broader concept.
So אימא *eima*, so רבא Rava *Rava* would tell you no, נתנו
וכרכו *nasnu v'karcho*, you designated it, you made it ready to use
for the ספר *sefer* and you actually wrapped the ספר *sefer*, you
did in fact use it. Now למה לי נתנו וכרכו *lama li
nasnu v'karcho*? So why now if that's true, why do you need
both of them? Meaning if רבא Rava *Rava*, if what you're saying
is correct that it's referring to the fact that you actually wrapped
the ספר תורה *Sefer Torah* with it and that's the thing that
makes changes its status, just say that. Why does it, why does
this משנה Mishnah *mishna* say the first part and only the first
part? But why does it say that you designated it? Just say
you used it. So רבא Rava *Rava* says, ah, because I need
both. For something to gain the status, it needs both. Designation is
not enough, but using without designation is also not enough. That might
be an ad hoc use. You need to designate and use it
for something to have its status. So כי דרב חסדא *ki d'Rav
Chisda*, like רב חסדא Rav Chisda. *Rav Chisda*, דאמר רב חסדא Rav
Chisda, *d'amar Rav Chisda*, האי סודרא דאזמניה למיצר ביה תפילין tefillin *hai
sudra d'azmanei l'meitzar bei tefillin*. You have a kerchief that you have
designated it to use to be your תפילין tefillin *tefillin* bag, to
wrap your תפילין tefillin. *tefillin* in it. וצר ביה תפילין tefillin *v'tzar
bei tefillin*, and then you went and you did wrap your תפילין
tefillin. *tefillin*. You designated and you used. אסור asur למיצר ביה פשיטי
*assur l'meitzar bei peshitei*.
Then you can't use it to wrap for a wallet. You have
now made it תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedusha. *tashmishei kedusha*, something used with
תפילין tefillin *tefillin*. But you needed both things: designating and using. אזמניה
ולא צר ביה tzar bei, *azmanei v'lo tzar bei*, if you designated
without
wrapping your תפילין tefillin, *tefillin* in it, that's הזמנה לאו מילתא hazmanah
lav milta, *hazmana lav milsa*, designating is not enough. צר ביה ולא
אזמניה *tzar bei v'lo azmanei*, but similarly if you used it for
wrapping your תפילין tefillin *tefillin* without designating it, it was an ad
hoc usage, שרי למיצר ביה פשיטי *shari l'meitzar bei peshitei*, you can
use it for your money. Why? Because you need both. For it
to gain a status, you understand, it can't be ad hoc. No,
it was just for two seconds I was wrapping it. I didn't
make it my תפילין tefillin. *tefillin* bag. You have to but you
designate things also sometimes. so you don't go through with your plans,
so you need designation and use to change the status. So that's
now a clarification of רבא's Rava position, and that's why it says
by this כרכשתא karksheta that you then designated to use for a
ספר that it says if you designated it. Now in parentheses רבא
Rava. would say and used it, but the designating is an important
part of that and that's what's going on there. אוקיי, Okay, ולאביי
דאמר הזמנה מילתא היא, u-le-Abaye d'amar hazmana miltha hi, now but אביי
Abaye doesn't agree with רב חסדא. אביי Abaye, would say that הזמנה,
hazmanah the designating, suffices. Again, maybe with an action, maybe without. ולאביי
דאמר הזמנה מילתא היא, אזמניה אע"ג דלא צר ביה, u-le-Abaye d'amar hazmana
miltha hi, azminei af al gav de-lo tzar bei, designating it even
without wrapping your תפילין tefillin gives it the status of תשמישי קדושה.
tashmishei kedusha, אוקיי, Okay, צר ביה, but if you wrap, but he
does agree that using it by itself does not suffice. Designating, it
all is about the designating. Designating suffices, using by using has no
meaningful, you know, doesn't make it anything better, doesn't do anything by
itself. You don't need it and it doesn't do anything by itself.
אוקיי, Okay, צר
ביה אי אזמניה, tzar bei ei azminei, if you wrapped תפילין tefillin.
then the only thing that doesn't matter. The only thing that matters
is did you designate? If you designated it, yes, it becomes the
status of a תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedushah לא אזמניה לא lo azminei
lo and if you did not designate, no. So now we have
clarity. In that world of designating, verbally or through an action, and
then using, רבא Rava. says for to have a status you need
both, and אביי Abaye. says for to have a status the only
thing that matters is designating.
Using it doesn't isn't needed in addition, it doesn't do anything by
itself. The only thing that gives it its status and that suffices
is designating for אביי, Abaye the הזמנה. hazmanah אוקיי, Okay, תא
שמע, ta shma, come in here.
נפש שבנאו לשם חי, nefesh she-banao le-shem chai, if you made a,
you know, like a tombstone, let's call it, some type of a
structure on top of the grave, if it is for the sake
of the living. Now what does it mean the sake of the
living? It's a tombstone. But it means the guy who it's made
for, his grave, he's still alive. So since that guy is still
alive, remember, these things get their status only because they're connected to
a corpse. There's no corpse yet. אוקיי, Okay, so since there's no
corpse yet it can't have any status even though you're going it's
purpose is to use eventually when the guy dies. So therefore מותר
בהנאה mutar be-hana'ah you can derive benefit. הוסיף בו דימוס אחד לשם
מת, hosif bo dimos echad le-shem met, now after you had this
whole thing and it's permissible in הנאה, hana'ah, then the guy actually
dies. Now that he's dead and you actually have a corpse, now
you add like a row of bricks, you add some piece to
it, in that case אסור בהנאה asur be-hana'ah it is forbidden. That
affects the whole status and the whole thing is like you've done
something, you've designated it and you actually have a corpse. So once
again that seems to be a proof like אביי. Abaye Once you
have that corpse, even before you put the corpse in the grave,
it is enough to do an action at least, but to designate
it and that gives it its status. So the גמרא Gemara says
no. הכא במאי עסקינן דרמיה ביה מת. hacha be-mai askinan de-ramya bei
met. We're talking that the body was already put in the grave
and אוקיי, okay, אי הכי מאי איריא דהוסיף כי לא הוסיף נמי.
ei hachi mai irya de-hosif ki lo hosif nami. So we're back
to our question. So אוקיי, okay, if you actually put the dead
body in the grave, then why shouldn't the once the guy dies
and you put him in the grave, why do you need this
extra row of bricks? Why shouldn't the tombstone itself get the status?
So we're going to have the same answer we had before. הוסיף
נמי לא, צריכא אע"ג דפנייה. hosif nami lo, tzericha af al gav
de-panya. We're talking about the case that then the body was removed.
So you put the body in and then you removed. As long
as the body is in, it's true, the tombstone is connected to
the body, it has a status. But now you removed it. So
that's just like the תפילין. tefillin. You used the tombstone with the
dead body, but it was out without designation. Since it was without
designation because when it was designated the guy was alive, so it
wasn't sort of designated, you know, when after he had died, without
designation then it only has its status when it's being used, but
when it's no longer being used, just like the using the handkerchief
to wrap the תפילין tefillin, because it was never designated as such,
it goes back to its original status and it is permissible. אוקיי,
Okay,
however, if you actually made the row of bricks, then you designated
it, then the guy died, right the guy or the guy died,
you made the row of bricks, you designated it, then you buried
him, then it fully has that status even if you remove him.
אוקיי, Okay, so really using the same structure as before that even
for רבא Rava, you need for something to get the status and
hold it. It might have the status when in use, but to
get the status and hold it it needs designation and and use.
אוקיי, Okay, אמר רב פפא בר פפא אמר רב חסדא אם היה
מכירו חוצו מותר. amar Rav Pappa bar Pappa amar Rav Chisda im
hayah mikiro chotzo mutar. If you can identify
the
bricks that you actually laid and now you can remove those bricks,
then the thing goes back to its original status because the thing
that made it designated has been reversed. Now by the way, again,
this seems to be that the designation of an אביי ורבא Abaye
ve'Rava or whatever הזמנה hazmana. is through an action, because clearly once
the guy dies, you can like verbally say, you know, whatever, it's
clear you're planning on using this tombstone. Although again, maybe in this
case, you know, verbal designation isn't enough because it's attached to the
ground. But what's clear is you need the designation that comes through
the action of laying the bricks, and that plus the guy, you
know, once you have the corpse and then you bury him that
gives it its status. Okay, but if you reverse that act of
designation, as it were, you take the bricks away, then it does
not have that status. Okay, so okay. תא
שמע, Tashma, come and hear. החוצב קבר לאביו, Ha'chotzev kever l'aviv, so
we quoted this yesterday. Somebody use H-E-W carvings out from the top
whatever, you know, a grave for his father, okay, in one of
those catacombs. והלך וקברו בקבר אחר, Ve'halach u'kevaro be'kever acher, and then
in the end the father was buried somewhere else. הרי זה לא
יקבר בו עולמית, Harei zeh lo yikaver bo olamis, so you cannot
use that for anybody else. Why? And we're assuming because it's אסור
בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Now that's a pretty funny assumption again because this
is like it's קרקע עולם, karka olam, which is sort of what
the גמרא Gemara asked before. So even assuming it's אסור בהנאה assur
b'hana'ah is funny. The other thing that's also funny, which is, is
that you know, why can't I use it for another dead body?
I could've used it for the guy could've used it for his
father's body, that's not considered הנאה, hana'ah, that's using it for the
dead. So why is now using it for another dead considered to
be הנאה hana'ah that you're getting from it? Maybe, you know, it's
being used for the dead, but again, it's saving you the cost
of another of digging another one. But, you know, just because it's
once it's designated for the dead, it should be able to be
used for any dead body. So I'm not exactly getting the הוה
אמינא hava amina besides that we're talking about קרקע עולם, karka olam,
you know once something is designated for the dead, why is it
considered הנאה, hana'ah, which is implicit because that's the גמרא Gemara understanding
that the problem using it for someone else is to use it
for another dead body. Okay, anyway but that's the question. So you
see הזמנה מילתא, hazmanah milsa. you dug the cave even before you
used it and that gives it its status.
התם משום כבוד אביו. Hasam mishum kevod aviv. No, that has nothing
to do with הזמנה מילתא. hazmana milta, That is specifically about your
father, that because it had been designated for your father, it doesn't
get any הלכה halacha status. Socially, it's disrespectful to use it for
somebody else. But if it had been dug for ראובן, Reuven, you
could use it for שמעון, Shimon, okay? It's just specifically this guy's
father. הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistavra, that makes sense. דקתני סיפא,
De'katani seifa, in the end it says, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, אף החוצב אבנים לאביו והלך וקברו במקום
אחר הרי זה לא יקבר בהן עולמית, af ha'chotzev avanim l'aviv ve'halach
u'kevaro be'makom acher harei zeh lo yikaver bahen olamis, that it's not
limited to digging the grave. Even somebody that's hewing, cutting out rocks,
you know, quarrying rocks to use that to build, I don't know,
a mausoleum or whatever, to build a you know some type of
a catacomb, whatever they're building it for the grave of the father,
those rocks can't even be used for a different body, for a
different corpse.
אי אמרת בשלמא משום כבוד אביו, Ei amart bishlama mishum kevod aviv,
if the concern is honoring or the problem of disrespecting your father,
שפיר, shapir, that makes sense. Why even even cutting out the stones
is a problem. אלא אי אמרת משום הזמנה, Ella ei amart mishum
hazmanah, but if it's about designating and that's what the status is
and it's not about specifically about the father, טווי לאריגה מי איכא
למאן דאמר, tvei l'ariga mi ika le'man d'amar, אביי Abaye, was only
talking about weaving it, where at the end of the day you
when you finish, you have the product that's going to be used.
So through an action, maybe verbally the designation of the project that's
in a state ready to be used gives it a status. But
here, it's like you it's like you were like you know spinning
the thread to be used in a in a what do you
call it in a shroud. Nobody would say spinning the thread gives
it its status. It's not yet in a state ready to be
used. So same with the stones. So clearly what's going here about
the father's grave has nothing to do with הזמנה hazmana and איסור
הנאה, issur hana'ah, it has to do with the honoring of the
father. Okay, תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear.
קבר חדש מותר בהנאה. Kever chadash mutar b'hana'ah. If you have a
new grave,
you know, and the assumption here is means new meaning it was
dug for a corpse but has yet to be used. Okay, so
like exactly the type of case we're dealing with. קבר חדש מותר
בהנאה Kever chadash mutar b'hana'ah is permissible in benefit. נתנה בו נפל
אסור בהנאה. Nitna bo nefel assur b'hana'ah. Once however a you know
a body has been put in even if it is a miscarriage,
that is considered to be a corpse and it makes it forbidden.
Again, interesting question here about קרקע עולם, karka olam, you know like
the גמרא Gemara said before, we should be talking about a case
about like קבר בנין kever binyan that we're talking more like some
mausoleum type thing, you know some type of a structure on top.
Whatever. Doesn't matter. Right now bracket that. The point is, it seems
very clear that this is רבא's Rava teaching: designating is not enough,
only once something, a body, is put in.
היטיל אין לא היטיל, Heitil in lo heitil, only when you put
the body in, not before that. Seems a very clear proof like
רבא. Rava The גמרא Gemara says no, הוא הדין דאף על גב
דלא היטיל, Huo din de'af al gav delo heitil, even before you
put the fetus in, דאפוקי מדרבן שמעון בן גמליאל דאמר אין לנפלים
תפיסת הקבר כמשמע לן, De'afuki miRabban Shimon ben Gamliel de'amar ain lanefalim
tefisas hakever kamashma lan, and this is coming to show that we
are against רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who says
that a fetus, like a miscarried fetus, does not affect the status
of the grave, does not sort of designate a grave and does
not make it אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So what does that mean?
אביי Abaye would say when it says if it's a new one
it's permissible, it means if it's made for somebody who's living it's
permissible. However, I mean it's a hard read of this but whatever.
However, if it's made for a fetus, you know, for the dead,
even a fetus, then it is forbidden and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, if it's for the fetus it
is not forbidden. Okay, בחדש Behadash would mean for the living and
then it's not about putting the fetus in, it's being made for
the fetus. All right, so that's אביי, Abaye but the simple read
of that is definitely like רבא. Rava
All right, תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear. מותר המתים למתים, Mosar
hamaysim lamaysim, if you collect money for, you know, for like the
חברה קדישא Hevra Kadisha society, you collect money to be used to
help in the burial costs and expenses for those that don't have,
you know, the money to do it. And then you have money
left over, you know, from your immediate needs, okay, you put it
away and that's designated for future dead bodies. All right, fine, that
makes sense. מותר המת ליורשיו. Mosar hamayis layorshav. However, if you go
around and you're collecting צדקה tzedakah for the burial of a particular
person, a particular corpse, and there's more money left over at the
end after all the funeral expenses and whatever, then the heirs get
to keep the money.
ותניא עלה כיצד, Vesanya alah keitzad, and we have a ברייתא Braisa
that clarifies this. How is this true? That was a משנה in
שקלים. Shekalim. And now here's what the ברייתא Braisa says: How is
this true? גבו למתים סתם, Gavu lemaysim stam, if you just said
we're collecting for funeral costs, זה מותר המתים למתים, zeh mosar hamaysim
lamaysim, that's a case when anything left over goes to the dead.
גבו למת זה, Gavu lemais zeh, if you collected specifically for ראובן
Reuven after he was dead, זהו מותר המת ליורשיו, zehu mosar hamayis
layorshav, that goes down to, that goes to the heirs. So you
see that designating the money for the use for this person is
not enough to give it the status of like, you know, connected
to the מת mais and of איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah.
So now you might be saying this is just money, didn't we
say that the thing has to be in a state that's ready
to be used, but תוספות Tosafos like you know not threads but
actual garments, but תוספות Tosafot says since money can easily be transferred
into any object that you need, that is considered to be in
the state ready to be used. That's a really fascinating and important
point. Anyway,
okay, so you see that the designating does not make the money
considered to be אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah or connected, you know, to
the
מת. mais. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at the end of that
ברייתא. Braisa. רבי מאיר אומר לא יגע בהן עולם עד שיבוא אליהו.
Rebbi Mayer omer lo yiga bahen olam ad sheyavo Eliyahu. רבי מאיר
Rebbi Mayer says no, even in that case of collected for ראובן,
Reuven, I, you know, the heirs cannot use that money. That money
has to be put away until אליהו Eliyahu can come and tell
us whether it should go to the heirs or you know whether
it should, I don't know, we'll see, we'll see what רבי נתן
Rebbi Nosson suggests. רבי נתן אומר יעשנו דימוס על קברו, Rebbi Nosson
omer ya'asenu dimus al kivro, you have leftover money, do something fancier
that you weren't expecting, make a nice, you know, gravestone, או זילוף
לפני מיטתו, o ziluf lifnai mitaso, or use it for like, you
know, incense or like, you know, air freshener, sprinkling wine to freshen
up the air, you know, around his bier, the funeral bier. So
use the funds for that מת. mais. All right, so that explains
what and you know and רבי מאיר Rebbi Mayer says I don't
know if they should, רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson says they belong to
the מת, mais, to ראובן, Reuven, and you'll figure out a way
to use it for ראובן. Reuven. And the first תנא קמא Tana
Kama says they go to the heirs and רבי מאיר Rebbi Mayer
is in a middle position. So how do you explain this debate?
So you could have said it's exactly the debate of אביי Abaye
and רבא, Rava. that the תנא קמא Tana Kama says designating doesn't
make it forbidden, it goes to the heirs. רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson
says it does make them forbidden, it goes to the מת, mais,
and רבי מאיר Rebbi Mayer has a ספק. suffek. But the גמרא
Gemara is now going to say that אביי Abaye and רבא Rava.
can both read it, that all the positions work with them. Let's
take a look. אלא אביי מתרץ לטעמיה ורבא מתרץ לטעמיה. Ella Abaye
metaretz leta'ameh veRava metaretz leta'ameh. אביי מתרץ לטעמיה, Abaye metaretz leta'ameh, אביי
Abaye explains his reasoning, רבא Rava. his reasoning. אביי מתרץ לטעמיה דכולי
עלמא הזמנה מילתא, Abaye metaretz leta'ameh dechulei alma hazzmana milsa, everybody would
agree that designating makes it forbidden.
Okay, here. The Tanna Kamma, תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, סבר דחזו לטפיס
דלא חזו לא טפיס. savar dechazu letaphis de lo chazu lo taphis.
But the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma just holds it's type of like
ברירה. breira. You know, retroactively we find out that the burial cost
only $1000 and not $1500, fine. So only $1000 becomes clarified were
designated. The other stuff was extra, so therefore was never retroactively or
whatever implicitly designated. Fine. רבי מאיר מספקא ליה טפי ולא טפי. Rabbi
Meir mesafke lei tafi lo tafi. Rabbi Meir doesn't know. Since at
the time you were assuming you needed it all, so maybe that's
enough even though it turned out that it wasn't all necessary. Maybe
still that's considered to be a הזמנה. hazmana He doesn't know if
it gets a status or not. הלכך לא יגע בהן עד שיבא
אליהו. Hilkach lo yigga ben ad sheyavo Eliyahu. Don't touch them until
אליהו Eliyahu comes. רב נתן פשיטא ליה דודאי טפיס. Rav Natan peshite
lei devadi taphis.
Rav Natan has no—you collected it for this מת meis even if
it winds up that it was more than what you were expecting
than the standard cost. Since it was designated at the time, it
has that status.
הלכך יעשה דימוס על קברו. Hilkach yasei dima'as hakiver. Okay, so for
אביי Abaye, the reason those positions say that it doesn't—you know, it
doesn't get designated or might not get designated is because the excess
funds maybe were considered never appropriate or needed, you know, for that
מת meis in hindsight. Now how—let's see how רבא Rava, is going
to explain רב נתן, Rav Natan, that it does get designated. רבא
מתרץ לטעמיה, Rava mitaretz leta'amei, לכולי עלמא הזמנה לאו מילתא היא. lechulei
alma hazmana lav milta hi. Everybody agrees fundamentally הזמנה hazmana is nothing.
תנא קמא סבר כי בזו ליה אחולי מחיל זילותיה גבי ירשין.
Tanna Kamma savar ki bazu lei achulei machli zilutei gabei yorshin.
Now the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, so the point, this is
sort of telling us what the idea of רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
is going to be. הזמנה hazmana. is not מילתא, milta, so it
should go to the יורשין. yorshin. The only thing, the extra—the only
thing is that it's like disrespectful to the dead that money that
was collected for the sake of his funeral, now the יורשין yorshin
are going to take it and they're going to go out to
dinner with the leftover money. That's not so respectful. That's the concern,
whether it's respectful or not. It doesn't really have a status. So,
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds that you know, that even though
it's a little disrespectful, the deceased would have wanted his heirs to
be able to have that money. So he forgoes any rights—you know,
he doesn't mind the disrespect in his death, whatever that's coming to
him. ורבי מאיר מספקא ליה מחיל או לא מחיל. VeRabbi Meir mesafke
lei machli o lo machli. Rabbi Meir's unsure whether he would be
okay with them using the money that way. Might be that disrespect—you
know, he wouldn't want that disrespect that would come from that. הלכך
לא יגע בהן. Hilkach lo yigga ben. Don't touch them. ורב נתן
פשיטא ליה דלא מחיל. VeRav Natan peshite lei delo machli. And for
רב נתן Rav Natan it's clear. Yes, הזמנה hazmana is לאו מילתא,
lav milta, it doesn't technically have a status, but the deceased would
not want you using the leftover money to go out to dinner
and a movie. הלכך יעשה דימוס על קברו. Hilkach yasei dima'as hakiver.
Therefore for the issues of respect, you got to use it to
do something on the grave, או זילוף לפני מטתו o ziluf lifnei
mitaso or type of air freshening and sprinkling. Okay. Wow, we've written
a lot of good proofs and a lot of ways of navigating
it. תא שמע. Ta shema. Last line on מ"ח עמוד א'. mem
chet amud aleph. היו אביו ואמו מזרקין בו כלים. Hayu aviv veimo
mizarkin bo kelim. מצוה עליכם להצילן. Mitzvah aleichem lehatzilan.
So you see the mother and father are in this terrible grief
over the death of their child and they are doing things that
people do in their grief and they're throwing all this stuff. We
actually know from various records or whatever in the גמרא, Gemara, outside
the גמרא, Gemara, that people would actually you know, put clothing and
jewelry and other types of things at times like in the grave.
Okay. And that would become connected—seen as connected to the corpse and
be אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So the parents are like being very
excessive and throwing all of this stuff in their grief. So it
says מצוה עליכם להצילן. mitzvah aleichem lehatzilan. If people are seeing this,
they should try to prevent the clothes from coming in contact with
the dead, which would give them their forbidden status and to try
to save you know the clothing and save these or the jewelry
or whatever because in you know, even though that's how the parents
are feeling now, they will be glad for the fact that this
person you know intervened later on when they're beyond their immediate anguish.
So anyway, the point is you see that only when the stuff—that
they can be saved. It's only going to be a problem when
the stuff comes in contact. So that proves like רבא. Rava, So
top of מ"ח עמוד
ב'. mem chet amud bet. התם משום מריריהו. Hatam mishum merirayhu. No,
no, no. אביי Abaye, would say because they're casting it in this
tremendous state of anguish and bitterness, okay, it's not real הזמנה. hazmana.
It's not the הזמנה hazmanah. they would do. They wouldn't want to
do this when they had calmed down. So this—so the fact that
they're designating in this state is not a meaningful הזמנה. hazmanah אי
הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, היינו דתניא עלה. hainu detanya
alah. How do you explain what it says on it? אמר רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל במה דברים אמורים שלא נגעו במטה אבל נגעו במטה
אסורין. Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel bameh devarim amurim shelo nag'u bamittah.
Aval nag'u bamittah assurim. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says when is that true—if it—I'm sorry, I like anticipated רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel before. Okay,
so yeah, I'm sorry, it's a רש"י Rashi says, excuse me, let's
back up. רש"י Rashi says before the—I jumped ahead with רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רש"י Rashi says... The idea of
להצילן lehatzilan is they, the parents threw the clothing and it went
into the coffin, and nevertheless מצוה על אחרים להצילן mitzvah al acherim
lehatzilan is you should take them out of the coffin so they
don't get buried with the corpse. Okay, that was the להצילן. lehatzilan.
So that really shows that הזמנה לאו מילתא, hazmanah lav milta. that
even when it's sort of touching the dead body, it hasn't really
been yet buried with it and it really has not yet been
used in a way that makes it considered connected to the dead
body and that shows הזמנה לאו מילתא. hazmanah lav milta. Okay, and
the גמרא Gemara says no, you know, that's only because they don't
really mean to do הזמנה. hazmanah Okay, now
and the גמרא Gemara says well one minute, let's take a look.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, במה דברים אמורים bameh
devarim amurim שלא נגעו במיטה? shelo nagu bamikta? When do they have
this status? Only if they haven't touched the actual funeral bier. אבל
נגעו במיטה אסורין, aval nagu bamikta asurin, once they touch it, it's
forbidden. So how do you explain that? It hasn't yet been buried
with the dead, it's only touched it. How does it get that
status? So clearly for
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, you
know,
their intent to designate it is meaningful, and somehow coming combined with
the fact that it touched the funeral bier. So whether that's because
it's like הזמנה hazmanah, plus usage and they consider that usage, or
whether it's just no, that's just you know, a meaningful הזמנה hazmanah
for רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, but either way
for him, you know, their intent is meaningful. We don't say because
they're in a fevered state. So and nevertheless for the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma it doesn't change the status. So certainly at least you
see that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and maybe even רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, right, are going like רבא. Rava
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says תרגמה עולא
במיטה הנקברת עמו targemah Ulla bemikta hanikberet imo דמחלפי בתכריכי המת. demichalfi
betachriche ha-met.
So עולא Ulla says we're talking about the actual not just the
bed he died in, and again I was jumping ahead the funeral
bier, we're not talking just the bed he died in, we're talking
about the bier, you know, the bier that they're actually going to
bury him with. And the reason to make it forbidden is not
because of הזמנה, hazmanah it's that if we let you take the
clothes after you threw them into the funeral bier and you took
them out of or let's say the coffin after you threw them
into the coffin, then you took the clothes out, right, then it's
going to look like even the actual תכריכין tachrichin shrouds that a
dead person are buried in are permissible. So it's a גזירה. gezeirah.
Okay, so to repeat, what do we have by here? We had
that stuff was being thrown on the dead body and that was
not enough to change its status. So it seems like הזמנה לאו
מילתא. hazmana lav milta. The גמרא Gemara tries to say it has
to do with their fevered state but rejects that and it says,
you know, fine, that's not what it's about. הזמנה hazmanah, but
no, excuse me, it is about their fevered state because of their
fevered state for אביי, Abaye. their הזמנה hazmanah is not meaningful. And
nevertheless
the issue of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is
not because of הזמנה, hazmanah. the issue of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is because their הזמנה hazmana is not meaningful
because of their fevered state, it's just a גזירה gezeirah that it'll
become to be confused with funeral shrouds. Okay, תא שמע ta shema
come and hear. כיס שעשאו להניח בו תפילין אסור להניח בו מעות.
kis she'asao lehaniach bo tefillin assur lehaniach bo ma'ot. We're going back
to the תפילין. tefillin, Okay, and this is very clear about that
you need both levels if you or well let's take a look.
כיס שעשאו להניח בו תפילין אסור להניח בו מעות kis she'asao lehaniach
bo tefillin assur lehaniach bo ma'ot or that you need just הזמנה.
hazmana You made this bag to put your תפילין tefillin, in it,
you cannot use it for money. אסור להניח בו מעות. assur lehaniach
bo ma'ot. הניח בו תפילין יניח בו מעות. heniach bo tefillin yaniach
bo ma'ot. Okay, however, if you just ad hoc used it for
תפילין, tefillin, then you can use it for money. So that seems
clearly like אביי, Abaye. making it for תפילין is enough to give
it its status. We're back to the point that usage without designation
does nothing, but designation alone, this seems a clear statement like אביי.
Abaye So the גמרא Gemara says no, אימא עשאו והניח בו תפילין
אסור להניח בו מעות כדרב חסדא. eima asao vehaniach bo tefillin assur
lehaniach bo ma'ot kiderav Chisda. No, no, no, it means if you
designated it in addition to using it, that's when it becomes forbidden
like רב חסדא, that you need designation and use. However, if you
just used it without designation, that's not enough. Okay, not פשט peshat
but that's what we read into it. תא שמע ta shema come
and hear. אמר לאומן עשה לי תיק של ספר או נרתיק של
תפילין. amar le'uman aseh li tik shel sefer o nartik shel tefillin.
Somebody says to a craftsman, make me, you know, a like a
mantle for a ספר תורה or bag for my תפילין. עד שלא
נשתמש בהן קודש מותר להשתמש בהן
חול. ad shelo nishtamesh bahen kodesh mutar lehishtamesh bahen chol. This is
quite explicit like רבא. Rava, Before you've used it for the holy
object, then it's not yet considered תשמישי קדושה and you can use
it for mundane objects. נשתמש בהן קודש אסור להשתמש בהן חול. nishtamesh
bahen kodesh assur lehishtamesh bahen chol. Once you've used it for the
holy purpose with the holy object, it gets
its status
and you. So the גמרא Gemara says you know what תנאי היא,
Tannai hi, fine, you've proven that there is a תנא Tanna that
holds that. We're going to say it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim.
Certainly a lot of the evidence earlier seemed to go like אביי.
Abaye דתניא Detanya ציפן
זהב או שהטיל להן עור של בהמה טמאה פסולות. tzipan zahav o
shetila lan o shel behema tmeia pesulot. If you covered your תפילין
with gold or used the leather of a non-kosher animal, they're invalid.
או בהמה טהורה כשרות. o behema tehora kesherot. However if you use
a the leather of a kosher animal, it's good, אף על פי
שלא עיבדן לשמה, af al pi shelo ibdan lishma, even though you
did not tan the leather and like you know prepare the leather
for the sake of תפילין. It does not need to be designated.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אף עור בהמה טהורה פסולות עד שיעבדן
לשמה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer af or behema tehora pesulot ad
she-ye-abdan lishma. No, you need to prepare them לשמה lishma in order
for it to work for תפילין. Now it is not at all
clear what this is doing with הזמנה hazmana מילתא, alright. We're talking
about whether the leather is kosher or not kosher for the תפילין,
not when it gets its status and so on. So רש"י Rashi,
says you know that that if you look at רש"י, Rashi אף
גב שלא עיבדו, af gav shelo ibdo, רש"י Rashi says לאור זה
לשמו דהזמנה לאו מילתא היא ולא איכפת לן בה. le-or ze lishmo
de-hazmana lav milta hi velo ikhpat lan bah. So that since you
know since that הזמנה hazmana is לאו מילתא, lav milta, so going
like רבא, Rava, so it doesn't matter if you do it for
the sake or not for the sake. Now that's a little funny
first of all because first of all that was about when something
gets the forbidden status, not whether something is kosher. But also even
if for רבא, Rava, you know, for רבא Rava. needed for something
to get its status needed both הזמנה hazmana and usage. So if
that's what you need to get its אסור status and you want
to make an analogy to תפילין, you would say that you need
both even for רבא, Rava. הזמנה hazmana and usage, and it has
to be לשמה. lishma. So it's not really clear how this links.
תוספות Tosafot does it in the reverse. תוספות Tosafot, says that if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות says like this,
ומפרש רבינו תם u'mefaresh Rabbeinu Tam about six lines down in the
narrow lines, דרבא דאמר הזמנה לאו מילתא היא סבר כרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל דבעי עיבוד לשמה משום דלא סגי בהזמנה. de-Rava de-amar hazmana lav
milta hi savar ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel de-ba'ei ibud lishma mishum de-la
sagi be-hazmana. That no, that according to אביי Abaye. that הזמנה hazmana
is enough, so fine, you know you're planning on using the leather
for תפילין, that gives it its status. רבא, הזמנה hazmana isn't enough,
so you need to actually do the עיבוד לשמה. ibud lishma. Okay,
again it's a little funny because why isn't it enough and therefore
go ahead and then use it for the תפילין, you know, use
it to make the box, it's הזמנה hazmana and usage. So not
at all clear how this makes it a מחלוקת תנאים, machloket Tannaim,
but I think we could certainly say that from the evidence brought
earlier there are תנאים Tannaim that are that seem to definitely feel
that you need הזמנה and use and others feel that הזמנה alone
suffices. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's see how
we פסקן. pasken. אמר ליה
רבינא לרבא.
Amar leih
Ravina l'Rava. רבינא Ravina said to רבא, מי גודוכא דרמו ביה מת
וארגי בגד למת? mi gudocha de-ramu beih met ve-argei beged l'met? He
says, I don't get the scenario you and אביי were talking about.
You got a dead body, because right, it only works when there's
already a dead body, and you're busy weaving a garment, like the
case you gave is one that's hard to imagine. Wouldn't it be
disrespectful for a dead body to be weaving a garment when it's
already there? You know, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה אין
כגון שכבי דהרפניא, amar leih in k'gon shikhvei de-Harpania, like the dead
in this place called Harpania where people were very poor and you
needed to collect the money to and then I guess make the
shrouds. You wouldn't have premade shrouds. You needed to start getting you
know and it collect the money only
after the person died. So sometimes yes, there is time that it
takes time to get all that stuff ready and you would have
that scenario. Okay,
last point about this.
דרש מרימר הלכתא כוותיה דאביי. Darash Mareimar hilkhata k'vateih de-Abaye. Mareimar ruled
like אביי. ורבנן אמרי הלכתא כוותיה דרבא. Ve-rabbanan amri hilkhata k'vateih de-Rava.
The rabbis say the הלכה halacha is like רבא. והלכתא כוותיה דרבא.
Ve-hilkhata k'vateih de-Rava. We rule like רבא. This is not one of
the יע"ל קג"ם. Ya'al Kegam. Okay, so הזמנה לאו מילתא. You need
הזמנה plus actual use in order for something to have its status.
Okay, that was a really important big conceptual סוגיא. sugya. Now we
switch gears and go back to the court executing people. And we'll
just do a little bit more for now. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
הרוגי מלכות נכסיהם למלך. Harugei malkhut nikhseihem l'melekh. If somebody is killed
by the king, you know in like a
non-judicial non-בית דין beit din type of a court, the king because
the king has power you know to judge on his own, maybe
it's also specifically in the context of מורד במלכות, mored b'malkhut, somebody
who rebels against the king. So if it's done by the king
then it goes to the property is seized by the king. הרוגי
בית
דין נכסיהם ליורשין. Harugei beit din nikhseihem l'yorshin. However if somebody is
executed by the court, the heirs inherit the property. Why not? Okay,
I mean you know. however somebody died,
the estate is inherited by the heirs. רבי יהודה אומר אף הרוגי
מלכות נכסיהם ליורשים, Rabbi Yehuda omer af harugei malchus nichseihem l'yorshim, so
right the חידוש chiddush is to claim that by the case of
killed by the king, it goes to the king. And that's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says I don't
agree. If it's killed by the king it also goes to the
heirs. Why does the government, why you know, why does anybody get
right to the property in a case when somebody is executed? Okay.
אמרו ליה לרבי יהודה, amru lei l'Rabbi Yehuda, so the Rabbis said
to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, ולא כבר נאמר הנה בכרם נבות אשר
ירד שם לרשתו. v'lo kvar neemar hinei b'cherem Navot asher yerad sham
l'rishto. Behold he is in the vineyard of נבות Navot where he,
this is אחאב, Achav, you know went down to inherit it. So
it sounds like, I mean okay, you know, he killed at the
incitement of איזבל, Izevel, he killed נבות Navot in order to gain
his vineyard. So but the word לרשתו, l'rishto, it doesn't say to
seize it or to appropriate it, it says to inherit, makes it
sound that because that at the end of the day, you know,
he was entitled to inheriting it through because because נבות Navot was
הרוגי מלכות, harugei malchus, was killed by the king interestingly even though
unjustly and through false testimony. Okay. אמר להן, Amar lahen,
so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said back, בן אחי אביו היה וראוי
ליורשו היה. ben achei aviv hayah v'raoi l'yorsho hayah. He was his
cousin and he was he inherited it because he was related to
נבות Navot not because he was killed by the king. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולא הרבה בנים היו לו, v'lo harbei banim hayu
lo, but one minute didn't נבות Navot have a lot of children?
רש"י says I don't know why the גמרא Gemara how the גמרא
Gemara knows this, but okay. אמר להן אותו ואת בניו הרג. Amar
lahen oso v'es banav harag. Yeah, but he killed him and all
of his killed children so that he could inherit. It's like the
guy who was 130th in the line of succession to the English
throne and went about trying to kill all 129 people that were
came in between him. So anyway yes he did horrific things, he
killed this נבות Navot and he killed his kids. But in the
end his taking the property was not because of a right of
the king, it was because he was the remaining heir. שנאמר אם
לא את דמי נבות ואת דמי בניו ראיתי, Shene'emar im lo es
damei Navot v'es damei banav raisi, because I have seen the blood
of נבות Navot and his children. So you see he killed the
children. Sounds like a little Macbeth. ורבנן V'Rabbanan and the Rabbis would
say back ההוא בנים הראויים לצאת ממנו. hahu banim haroyim l'tzeis mimenu.
No, no, no, that's because the future children that he never had
because he was killed, but he did not but אחאב Achav himself
did not actually kill נבות's Navot's children. Okay. בשלמא למאן דאמר נכסיה
למלך היינו דכתיב ברך נבות אלהים ומלך. Bishlama l'man d'amar nichsei l'melech
hainu d'ksiv beirach Navot Elohim vaMelech.
If you say that it goes to the king that's why when
they raised these false accusations against נבות, Navot, you know איזבל Izevel
his wife sort of set this whole thing up that false witnesses
would come and testify that נבות Navot had blasphemed אלהים Elohim and
blasphemed and rebelled against ומלך. vaMelech. So he says I get so
that's why part of the claim was he rebelled against the king
in order that it would be a מורד במלכות, mored b'malchus, rebelling
against the king and they'd be entitled to his property. אלא למאן
דאמר נכסיה ליורשים, Ella l'man d'amar nichsei l'yorshim, but if the property
goes to the heirs, so למה לי ומלך? lama li vaMelech? Why
did they have to add to the false charges that he cursed
out the king? You don't need him to be a מורד במלכות
mored b'malchus in order, he'll inherit him because he's a relative you
know. So the גמרא Gemara says ולטעמך אלהים למה לי? u'l'taameich Elohim
lama li? Okay but even if we say that it goes to
the king because he was a מורד במלכות mored b'malchus and that's
why they said he blasphemed the king, why did they have to
say that he blasphemed אלהים? Elohim? That was that was completely irrelevant
to being able to seize the property. אלא לאפושי ריתחא, Ella l'afushei
ritcha,
so clearly even according to you that it's because he was a
מורד במלכות mored b'malchus he was entitled to the property and that's
why they said blaspheme the king, they added אלהים Elohim in order
to get the judges even angrier, you know, to make it such
a horrific thing and that they would be maybe easier to you
know to dupe them. הכא נמי לאפושי ריתחא, hacha nami l'afushei ritcha,
so for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda as well who says that the
king isn't entitled to the property, they said אלהים Elohim and ומלך
vaMelech in order to you know just get everybody really worked up
and angry. Okay we will end here for now.